hey everyone welcome again to another
lesson in this Tosca automation course
today we are going to talk about action
modes in Tosca now although in some of
my previous sessions I have already used
some of the action modes like input and
constraint
or weight on but we'll talk about all of
these action modes in more details and
we'll look at some of the examples using
this action modes
so what is an action mode action mode is
used to steer your test objects inside
your test cases it also defines how the
value in the value field of your test
case will be applied for the test step
values in order to steer your controls
now action modes which are available on
the x-step values depend on the
interface type either you are using a
GUI or non-jui then according to that
the action modes would be available in
your test cases in the respective test
values
the different action modes which are
available in Tosca are the following so
the first action mode is input
now this is very common action mode
which you must have seen while using
your Tosca so this is used to uh
basically input values into test objects
okay something like a edit box where you
are trying to input some value so you
will by default use this action mode
which is called input
and then there is insert now this insert
is for non-ui interface environments so
you will not see if you are using a UI
environment right UI based application
it is only for the non-ui applications
something like an XML file so it allows
you to create objects inside an XML file
right so you can use this insert
accident mode
the next is buffer action mode so if you
need input values and different test
steps or in different test cases right
so you can store these values or buffer
these values using this buffer action
mode so it is like a global variable
which can store some values and it can
be used across any of your test cases
okay
then there is constraint it limits the
search for a superordinate node and it
is mostly used with tables so we'll look
at an example where you will see that
when you are steering through a table
you can use this constraint mode or
constraint action mode in order to limit
your search for certain rows and columns
based on some particular values or
constraints okay
then there is verify action mode this is
basically used for verification a step
in your test cases so it allows values
and control properties and test objects
to be verified so this is also very
commonly used action mode because you
need to have a verification step in
every test case so probably you will be
using this verify action mode
then there is weight on it stops the
execution of the test case until the
property has the specified value now we
have seen an example but we'll look at
more examples of a weight on Action
Motor
and the last but final action mode is
Select now it allows you to select
specific nodes uh this also is pretty uh
useful in terms of steering tables so
we'll be looking at an example where
we'll see that the select action mode is
automatically
um used by Tosca whenever you are
staring through tables rows and columns
now let's try to use Tosca and see
um some of these action modes so we'll
be looking at how we can use the verify
constraint and select action modes while
steering a particular table in Tosca
so right now I have opened my Tosca and
here will be
recording some modules and we'll see how
we can use the different constraints to
share a particular table so for that
I'll be using this page where we have
got a table and as you can see there are
some rows and columns here right so what
we will do is we'll try to pick up a
particular row and we'll try to verify
if this email exists in that particular
row so that's what is our goal and we'll
achieve it through different action
modes in Tosca
so let's go ahead and scan this module
first
so I have created a particular folder
here and I'm going to scan this
particular application
select the respective application and
then click on scan as always
and then it will show you all the
different uh controls in this particular
page right out of these uh we just need
the table okay which is also called the
person's table okay and I'm going to
name this module as obstacle
um and I can name it action modes
okay
and then um I'm going to save it and
close it
okay
now um our module is ready and let's go
ahead and create a test case and we'll
see how we can use this particular
action modes in Tosca right so I'm going
to create a folder called action modes
yes
and inside this I'm going to create a
test case okay so I'm going to call it
verify
tables
so let's open the test case here and
then let's
put our module inside this so we have
got obstacle action modes
and we have now got our table right so
this is also an example where I will
show you how you can steer through a
different Dynamic web tables right so
when you scan a particular table it
automatically records the rows and
columns and you will also get
automatically all the different column
headers here right so we have got the
last name for a first name email action
and also you can select this dollar one
which will select the first row or you
can select the last row also or you can
also give it up any particular row using
this taller and inside this brackets
which is n and can be replaced by any
particular number okay
so basically you can select any row
depending on either the row number or
depending on these column headers okay
so what we want to do uh let's go back
here
um so let's select a particular example
here okay so let's see if we want to do
this J into right or we want to yeah
select this row
and then we want to verify whether the
email is correct or not which is
genetexample.com
so let's see how we can do this using
um different action modes okay
so first uh we need to steer through the
table so I'm going to select inside the
row I'm going to select this particular
cell okay so
um it will be the first name okay
and I'm going to change this action mode
as you can see all the action modes are
available here
and the particular action mode which we
are talking about select right so this
is the select action mode as you can see
Tosca has automatically used the select
action mode for the table and the row
because we are selecting this table and
the row in order to get to this cell
right so we need to use the action mode
to select here
and after that I'm going to use the
constraint mode here okay
and what the constraint action mode is
going to do is it is going to constraint
the search for this particular cell
based on the value which I provide for
this cell okay so here what I can say is
I can look for a value whose inner text
is equals equals Gene okay so that's the
value and it is a constraint
so this makes your search faster if
there are hundreds of rows it will look
for this particular constraint value and
then it will limit the search for that
particular row okay
um and then
once we have got the first name as the
gene right so this is the value which we
have given
so we don't need anything else because
this is unique in all of these rows
right this name doesn't exist here
anymore so I can limit my search based
on this first name equals to Jane right
and now I can go ahead and verify my
email okay so for this next cell I'm
going to select email
and this time I will leave the action
mode as verify okay and I will say
um here also I can use the inner text
right so in a text equals equals JN dot
do at example.com
okay
and let's see if the value is okay it's
Jane at example.com
so let me correct that
okay so that's that's my verification
step and that's my constraint so we have
used three action modes here select
constraint and verify okay and that's
our complete test case now let's try and
run this and see whether it works as
expected or not
so as you can see uh my execution has
passed and we'll look at the results now
okay
here you can see it will show you the
table and the rows which you have
selected right and it will only show you
login for the verification step right
not for the other steps and that is the
reason you should have a verification
step for each test case right
so here it is showing verification was
successful it will show you the expected
value which uh you have given jnet
example.com and that's also the actual
value which it has graphed from the
particular page right
now let me show you another example uh
how you can extend this for more
extensive scenarios like uh like the one
here uh where we have got this
um example called John right so this uh
particular test case will fail if I'm
going to change this particular row to
look for this John at example.com and
why because the first name is same in
both the rows right so you cannot use
constraint in just the first name and
get through your result it is going to
fail because there are two duplicate
rows with the same first name so in this
kind of cases what you can do you can
add more constraints to your particular
test steps right so I here we can use
the last name and the first name as
constraint so that it can limit the
search to this particular row okay so if
I'm using uh John do then it will go
ahead and search for this particular row
because there are two constraints
instead of just one constraint okay so
let's try and see how we can do this so
again the same thing
um
now let's change this
um and we will go for the last name
and here we will instead of example.com
or the email will look for John Jane do
okay
or John Doe
so we'll we'll look for
um the first name as John and the last
name as do okay and we'll change this
action mode to constraint
and then finally we'll verify so let's
do that and here again inner text
equals to John at example.com
okay
so uh that's how Tosca will decide which
row to select based on these two
constraints okay you can add any number
of constraints based on your scenario to
make the search Unique so that you can
uniquely search the particular row and
column where you want to perform that
particular action which whether it's a
verification step or you want to perform
some action on some other on particular
cell okay
so let's again run this and let's see if
it works
it'll pass it was uniquely able to
identify that particular row using the
constraints action mode and it was also
able to
verify our
email right so that's John example.com
so
that's how you can use all of these
three action modes which is constrained
verify and select
when you are steering through different
tables or which are dynamic in nature or
which has got these um
non-unique rows and columns so you can
steer through different rows uh uniquely
using this constraint action mode
so we'll look through some other action
modes like buffer and weight on in our
next session